crocha@ucsd.edu crocha700.github.io github: crocha700 vimeo: crocha700 ORCID: 0000-0003-4063-5468 18 Aug, 2016

# Cesar B Rocha

# Physical oceanographer

Research Physical oceanography, particularly the dynamics of unsteady mesoscale to submesocale flows, and the Brazil Current System. Geophysical fluid dynamics, particularly stirring and mixing in geophysical turbulence. Numerical methods, specifically Galerkin approximations. Data science and oceanographic big data.

## **Education**

Current, PhD in Oceanography, University of California, San Diego 2013 MSc in Oceanography, University of São Paulo, Brazil 2011, BSc in Oceanography, University of São Paulo, Brazil

## **Experience**

**2015**, Fellow in Geophysical Fluid Dynamics, GFD Program, WHOI Coupled reduced equations for strongly stratified flows.

**2013–Current, Graduate Student Researcher, SIO/UCSD** Stratified planetary turbulence and dynamics of the upper ocean.

**2012**, Visiting student, University of Massachusetts Dartmouth Quasigeostrophic modes and surface quasigeostrophic solutions.

**2011–2013**, **Master Student**, **University of Sao Paulo** Energetics and dynamics of the Brazil Current System.

## **Publications**

#### **Submitted**

- 2. Ardhuin, F., Gille, S., Menemenlis, D., Rocha, C. B., Rascle, N., Chapron, B., Gula, J., Molemaker, J.: Small scale currents have large effects on ocean wave heights, under review for GRL.
- 1. **Rocha, C. B.**, Chereskin, T. K., Gille, S. T., Young, W. R., and Menemenlis, D.: Seasonality in governing submesoscale dynamics in the Kuroshio Extension, under review for GRL.

#### Peer-reviewed

- 4. **Rocha, C. B.**; Chereskin, T. K.; Gille, S. T. and Menemenlis, D., 2016: "Mesoscale to submesoscale wavenumber spectra in Drake Passage", *J. Phys. Oceanogr.*, 46 (2), 601-620, doi:10.1175/JPO-D-15-0087.1.
- 3. **Rocha, C. B.**; Young, W. R. and Grooms, I., 2016: "On Galerkin approximations of the surface-active quasi-geostrophic equations", *J. Phys. Oceanogr.*, 46 (1), 125-139, doi:10.1175/JP0-D-15-0073.1
- 2. **Rocha, C. B.**; da Silveira, I. C. A., Castro, B. ,M. and Lima, J. A. M., **2014**: "Vertical structure, energetics and dynamics of the Brazil Current System at 22°S-28°S", *J. Geophys. Res.*, *119*, doi:10.1002/2013JC009143.
- 1. Rocha, C. B.; Tandon, A.; da Silveira, I. C. A. and Lima, J. A. M., 2013: "Traditional Quasi-geostrophic modes and Surface Quasi-geostrophic solutions in the Southwestern Atlantic", *J. Geophys. Res.*, 118 (5), doi:10.1002/jgrc.20214.

#### **Grey literature**

1. **Rocha, C. B.**, 2015: Coupled reduced equations for strongly stratified flows, Proceedings of the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Program, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Woods Hole, MA.

## **Invited Seminars**

1. Oceans and Cryosphere Seminar Series, Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Fall 2015

### Software

- 2. Core developer for "Python quasigeostrophic model" (PyQG), doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.30517
- 1. Core developer for "Spectral Analysis in Python" (PySpec), doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.31596

## **Service**

2016, Reviewer for DSR-I, GRL, JFM, Nature Comm.

2016, Member of student committee as part of the SIO faculty search in large scale observational physical oceanography.

2015-2016, Mentor for 1st yr SIO Graduate Students.

2015, Member of student committee for the SIO teaching award.

## **Honors & Awards**

2016, NASA Earth & Space Science Graduate Fellowship 2015, Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Fellowship, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution 2011, Best BSc thesis in Oceanography, University of Sao Paulo

### Skills

#### **Programming**

Python, C, Fortran 90, Shell-Script, Matlab, git, mercurial, markdown

#### Languages

English (fluent), Portuguese (native), Spanish (professional fluency)

# Membership

American Geophysical Union, The Oceanography Society, NumFOCUS

### Other interests

Data science, Scientific reproducibility, Free software, Open science, History and philosophy of science